In the heart of the French region of
Burgundy, the small town of Cluny holds
a secret. Once a gigantic church stood
here, now barely 1/10 of the original
remains.
In its day,
>> [music]
>> it was the largest Abbey in the world.
Its pillars rose more than 30 [music] m.
Its nave spanned 60 m longer than Notre
Dame de Paris.
300 windows [music] illuminated the
building.
It was called Maior Ecclesia,
>> [music]
>> Latin for the largest church.
>> It was an absolutely incredible
technical feat. They managed to build
something that was simply oversized for
the era.
>> Built by 11th century monks in less than
70 years, it would remain Western
Christianity's largest church for five
centuries,
defying all architectural standards and
declared a second [music] Rome.
>> It looked directly to the papacy in Rome
for direction.
>> But after the French [music] Revolution,
this pious Abbey was abandoned,
destroyed, and sold stone by stone.
>> The site completely deviated from the
concept of an Abbey.
>> For nearly a century, archaeologists and
historians have searched for traces of
the Abbey in the walls of the city.
They've discovered that the builders of
this church had mastered extraordinary
techniques. [music]
>> And so, they must have wanted to build
very high.
From from the from the word go, you
don't build vast foundations if you're
going to have a small church with
nothing on top of them.
>> How did the monks meet the challenge of
building such a tall and stately abbey
almost a thousand years ago? Where did
they find the materials? How did they
transport them?
Now the greatest experts on the Cluny
Abbey, meticulous computer-generated
reconstruction, and 20 years of hard
work will reveal the lost secrets of the
Maior Ecclesia.
Cluny Abbey was located in a remote
valley in the heart of Burgundy in
southeastern France.
Within the walls of the lost religious
[music] city once stood the largest
abbey ever built in the Middle Ages.
More than 90% destroyed [music] after
the French Revolution, only a few
vestiges remained, which was swallowed
up by the city that developed over the
centuries.
How could one [music] calculate the
dimensions of the original church? What
did it look like?
Today, only the large [music] southern
transept remains with its octagonal
tower, the last vestige that proves
[music] the once colossal size of the
building.
>> Because it's the only bit of Cluny
that's left, one forgets just how
gigantic it is.
And the transept that survives is, you
know, twice the size of the average
church, isn't it? In its own [music]
right. And it's only one of two
transepts.
>> The dimensions [music] of the tower were
unheard of for a building from the
Middle Ages.
It was more than 60 m high and
overlooked the valley.
The interior vaults measured up to 30 m.
This tower awakened the curiosity of
historians to [music] find the plans of
the missing Abbey.
Only one existed, preciously preserved.
It dates from 1700 [music]
and was made by an anonymous person.
The precision of the drawing is the only
trace of what this extraordinary [music]
church was like.
>> This is the oldest plan of the Abbey.
The earliest testimony to its existence
in Cluny.
It was a huge monastery.
To give you an idea, from the end of the
11th to the 12th century, it housed
approximately 300 monks.
At the height of its existence, Mont
Saint-Michel had only 80 monks.
So, it was truly colossal in size.
>> The Abbey was a veritable city that
stretched over 15 hectares, [music]
almost half the size of today's Vatican,
with buildings that were oversized for
the time.
Some are still visible [music] in the
city, such as the mill there
and the inn.
Yet, the highlight of the map that
intrigued the researchers [music]
was the size of the abbatial church in
the middle.
>> When you look at the scale of the large
abbatial church, you see that it was
colossal.
It was 187 m long.
To put it into proper perspective, it
was 60 m longer than Notre Dame de
Paris.
>> The church [music] was bigger than Notre
Dame de Paris, St. Peter's Basilica in
Rome, Chartres Cathedral, and the
Basilica [music] of Saint-Denis.
In size, it beat any other church in the
Middle [music] Ages.
Its unrivaled length held double aisles,
11 spans, [music] two transepts, a small
and large with a width of 75 m, a
chancel, and an apse composed of
multitudes of radiating chapels [music]
named apsidioles.
To understand [music] the size of this
monumental church, we must go back to
the time of its creation, which began
with a key asset.
>> The location on the site itself is
linked to a donation made in 1910 by the
Duke of Aquitaine.
He gave a plot of land and old villa to
a handful of monks.
But, he had the distinction of placing
this community under the direct [music]
responsibility of Rome.
>> It was directly
subservient or
looked directly to [music]
the papacy in Rome for direction.
So, it considered itself [music] in a
sense, I suppose, to be a second Rome.
>> [music]
>> Its direct attachment to Rome gave it a
privileged status, but the abbey became
even more important a few [music] years
after its creation thanks to a specific
event.
>> They brought relics to Cluny first of
St. Peter and St. Paul, and then relics
in numbers such as Cluny competed with
St. Peter's Basilica in Rome and gave
rise to a very large veneration of
relics.
>> One could come to venerate the relics of
St. Peter or at least pray around the
abbey. It was a bit like making a
pilgrimage to Rome. I'm slightly
exaggerating, but not much. There was a
very strong connection to Rome.
>> The first church called Cluny 1 quickly
became too small.
The monks built what was named Cluny II,
a little larger, but 20 years later this
church was deemed to be too narrow.
They then built Cluny III, the Maior
Ecclesia, or biggest church.
>> The idea was to build a church that
could perhaps accommodate up to 1,000
monks.
Or at least a very large number of them
that were either on site or passing
through.
It was absolutely vital to have
something more imposing that was really
in the image of this second Rome.
They wanted the best, the greatest, the
most beautiful, and the brightest to
manifest their faith in God.
Also to show his strength and his power.
And that the greatest, be they emperors
or even the pope, should do that with
Cluny.
At one point Rome could not do without
the Cluny Abbey.
The Abbot of Cluny was an essential
person in medieval Europe of the 11th
and 12th centuries.
Abbot [music] Hugh of Semur launched the
construction of Cluny III, the Maior
Ecclesia, in 1080.
His goal was to build the largest church
ever, but the monks were immediately
faced with a problem.
The location.
>> [music]
>> How could a huge church be built on a
cramped site at the junction [music] of
two rivers and on the steep slope of a
valley?
>> The site where Cluny was built wasn't
very good for construction.
In fact, it was somewhat of a flooded
basin. To the east there was the Grône
River that flooded often creating silt.
The soil was very unstable up to the
level where I'm at now, where natural
terrain began.
>> The heart of the church had to face east
towards Jerusalem, so the monks had to
level the hillside to create a base by
removing thousands of cubic meters of
earth.
>> These were considerable earthworks.
They had a bit of difficulty since they
were perpendicular to the slope of the
hill
and consequently were forced to carry
out a number of works to try to get it
leveled.
There were layers of land that were not
very homogeneous.
And the eastern parts were still quite
wet.
That's why they built extremely strong
foundations.
You need solid foundations to build
high. The Cluniac monks understood
[music] that very well.
The Chapel of Jean de Bourbon at the
extreme southeast of the abbatial church
[music] was redesigned in the 16th
century.
Excavations are underway to find the
ancient foundations of the Abbey led by
Fabrice Ouryou, an archaeologist at the
center of medieval studies.
>> What's quite extraordinary is that we're
in the foundations. This is extremely
well-designed and well-built masonry.
And yet it wasn't visible, but in the
ground, buried in the foundation
trenches.
It's a very high-quality construction.
>> The limestone blocks are perfectly cut.
Their thickness varies from 6 to 18 cm
and they're connected by mortar.
>> The foundations were deep because the
builders looked for hard ground to use
as a base.
Here They were really trying to make
deep, solid foundations in order to bear
the weight of the whole structure.
>> The depth of the foundations followed
the slope of the valley to reach the
hard rock, up to 4 m deep in certain
places.
They were also extremely thick. On the
western part of the transept, the
foundation wall was 5 m wide.
>> From the start,
the foundations were colossal. They're
big and they're very deep on a site
which is not easy to build on.
And so they must have wanted to build
very high.
From from the from the word go, you
don't build vast foundations if you're
going to have a small church with
nothing on top of them.
>> To stabilize the foundations, the monks
went even further.
Each wall and each pillar base were
connected [music] by 3.5 m thick
masonry.
All the structures were firmly anchored
to each other.
>> These walls were brought together,
including those under the arches.
So from one wall to another or from one
pillar to another, were foundations that
followed each other.
It's called a sill plate, which is a
kind of grid.
This grid stabilizing the soil was a way
of connecting the support points that
these pillars represented.
Once it was done, you could build
whatever walls you wanted.
>> If the ground moved, the entire building
moved, but it wouldn't fracture.
There lies the genius behind the
construction.
>> Engineers from the Ecole Nationale des
Arts et Métiers did a simulation and
realized that these foundations had
enormous purpose.
Had they not been there, the monument
wouldn't have stood.
>> At the beginning of the 20th century, an
archaeologist also took a keen interest
in the foundations of the lost [music]
church. American Kenneth John Conant
would change the fate [music] of the
Abbey.
>> When he arrived, everything was under
grass. There was no sign of of
foundations or anything like that. The
only thing that survived was the the
great transept and the little eastern
transept and the Chapel of Jean de
Bourbon and so on. That little group of
buildings, but apart from that, there
wasn't anything really visible.
>> The site had completely taken over the
area. It was a little like the Khmer
temples where vegetation invades the
temples. In Cluny, the city took over
the area, completely surrounding the
Abbey.
The site had completely deviated from
the concept of an Abbey.
So, Conant worked for nearly 40 years to
find not only the plan, but to
reconstruct the lost volumes of this
exceptional building.
>> Using rare artist drawings from the 18th
century showing the Abbey and its
church,
Kenneth John Conant [music] had only one
obsession, to find the exact dimensions
of the building.
To do so, [music] he analyzed the
foundations, their thickness, and their
composition, finally drawing hundreds of
plans which revealed the Abbey [music]
in volume for the first time.
>> Conant was the one who rediscovered the
Cluny Abbey.
He was the first to have proposed
reconstitutions of the abbatial church
in all its original and later splendor.
>> Through his research, Conant discovered
[music] the entire size of the building.
The nave of the church was composed of a
double [music] span punctuated by 18
monumental pillars.
It also featured a [music] transept
itself followed by a smaller one.
Finally, [music] there was the chancel
with 10 pillars that formed an
ambulatory.
Three floors of windows [music] bathed
the church in light.
And the vaults were 30 m high.
In the 11th [music] century, no other
church matched it in height and
dimensions. It was the largest, highest,
and brightest.
But how did the monks manage to create
such a masterpiece using the techniques
of the Middle Ages?
The 10th century was the golden age of
Romanesque art. Churches were modest in
size, not exceeding 20 m tall with thick
walls and small windows, far from
[music] what the monks wished to
achieve.
>> The churches of the 11th century were
darker, usually because their windows
were cut into the walls of the tribunes.
The naves were rarely lit directly.
>> [music]
>> The churches were rather squat.
The monks of Cluny decided to raise the
walls
to build very high vaults and to add
many windows.
>> At the time, the vaults had a
semi-circular arched shape, typical of
Romanesque art.
>> [music]
>> The semi-circle supported the weight.
The diameter was therefore equal [music]
to the width of the vault.
The height of the vault was the radius.
To increase the height, the nave had to
be widened. But the bigger it got, the
more the forces at hand weakened [music]
the structure.
To build higher, they had to find a
solution other than the semi-circular
arch.
>> They were driven by the necessity of
solving this technological problem to
guarantee the stability of the building.
At one point, the genius idea of using
Gothic arches must have come into the
mind of the site manager as a way to
solve this issue.
>> The Gothic arch is two half-circles with
[music] centers located at the
extremities of the vault.
They intersect, and this forms a Gothic
[music] arch.
The width is no longer related to the
diameter as it is for [music] the
semi-circular arch.
It can reach 2/3 of the arch.
It's therefore possible to build higher
than with a semi-circular arch.
>> The Gothic arch existed before Cluny.
It wasn't conceived specifically for
Cluny, but it was used because of its
interesting characteristics.
In the Romanesque style,
all arches were systematically
semi-circular.
For Cluny, however, they could not be
used for reasons of stability.
At that time, it was quite innovative
because it would allow the weight to be
better distributed over fully vaulted
parts.
>> With semi-circular arches, the weight is
evenly distributed horizontally and
vertically.
This requires thick walls to prevent
them from spreading under pressure.
By breaking the arch into two half
circles, the horizontal component of the
weight is reduced and carried over
[music] to the vertical component.
As a result, the walls can be thinner
and higher without the risk of
spreading.
>> From the moment these walls could be
higher in elevation,
they could also be cut more easily to
create bay windows.
It was these openings that allowed light
into all the vessels that made up the
nave and the aisles of Cluny III.
>> [music]
>> It's clear that behind what appears to
us to be essentially new forms,
there was above all technological
research
at a level we would deem quite advanced
today.
>> But gothic arches were not enough to
flood the nave with light while
maintaining the stability of the
building.
It is this church plan that allowed the
architects to grasp the level of mastery
with which the Cluniac monks understood
the [music] balance of forces.
>> This is a cross-section of the large
nave of Cluny III.
It was composed of a central aisle and a
double aisle.
The forces were redistributed by
staggering the aisles.
This shear distribution of lateral force
was achieved through the stability of
the outer walls with powerful
buttresses.
So, it was a massive structure, but a
particularly well balanced one.
There was a genuine effort made to
understand these forces.
These people displayed an exceptional
level of conceptualization.
There was a clear architectural and
engineering approach.
Typical of Romanesque art, the central
naves were buttressed with aisles.
Here, the size of the building is such
that the monks added a third aisle,
maintained by powerful outer buttresses.
The monks pushed Romanesque art to its
limits.
The three floors of successive Gothic
arch vaults rose to 29.5 m, 17 m, and 10
m, allowing for a perfect balancing of
forces.
It was then possible to cut rows of
windows on each floor.
These windows represented a 45% void
compared to the walls.
>> There were several rows of overlaid
windows, which obviously allowed them to
create an unrivaled luminosity inside.
This is to evoke another spirituality,
that of the divine that floods the place
of contemplation with his light.
>> At that time, people didn't dare open
walls under vaults like this, especially
in a building as important as the Maior
Ecclesia.
So, this was very important and very
bold, and it foreshadowed what Gothic
architecture would later become.
>> In Gothic art, the structure carries the
building, not the walls.
In Cluny, the monks pushed the thought
process of force distribution to an
extreme in order to exceed the heights
allowed in Romanesque art, right down to
details [music] essential to balance.
This is notably the case with the
position of the [music] pillars.
This narrowing, very subtle at each
level, allowed the springing point of
the vaults to be brought into the design
of the building and thus offer more
stability.
And so the oblique lateral strain was
better contained in the design of the
building.
The building was a balance between force
supplied vertically and horizontally:
buttresses, arches, and the position of
pillars.
Everything was present [music] to allow
the monks to build a gigantic church.
However, because the building was also
subject to torsional movement, the monks
paid attention to the slabs that
supported the top floor.
>> Well, now there was a whole system of
staples that actually locked the inner
bands. The last band at the top of the
transept. So, all the parts were
actually sealed by these metal staples.
>> These were large staples, 50 cm in
length by 2 cm in width and across.
The building was so large that they had
to take every precaution and resort to
any technique imaginable to achieve
stability and avoid deformation.
>> But that wasn't enough.
The monks were still concerned about the
pressure put on the walls by the vault.
So, they placed large iron bars along
the entire length of the nave.
>> Across the transept, there were these
bars of metal which held the thing
taut.
These huge tie rods of iron had to
hold the walls from
from falling outwards, you know?
>> If they did it, it was because there was
a need. So, it's clear that the building
called for this kind of buttress.
The project was rather bold anyway.
Everyone in the Middle Ages knew Cluny,
and the builders of the great cathedrals
knew it, too.
They knew what the advantages or
disadvantages of various strategies
were.
That's why the Gothic arch implemented
in Cluny was reproduced in the great
cathedrals.
The use of iron with staples was used in
Gothic architecture and so on.
The Abbey was splendid, grandiose, and
impressive.
The first stone was laid on October
25th, [music] 1088.
The monks began with the southern arm of
the great transept, the only part that
remains today.
The site then moved south to north and
then to the west.
On the walls of the church, you could
see a multitude of holes left by the
workers' scaffolding. These are called
putlog holes.
>> Putlog holes are small orifices that
were made into the wall
at the time of construction. That's how
they could stack the beams, trays,
scaffolding, and so on.
>> Their location provides information
[music]
on the evolution of the construction
site, notably the part that survived
[music] the destruction,
the large southern transept of the
Abbey.
We can [music] see that the putlog
holes, which are aligned horizontally on
the first two spans, are not on the
third.
There is a difference [music] of 30 to
40 cm.
This is a sign the construction stopped.
What happened?
If we look at the third span in [music]
more detail, the three highest windows
are not aligned with those just below.
Moreover, the band that marks the floor
suddenly stops and does not continue on
the third span.
All [music] of these clues help us
understand what happened on the site at
that time.
>> There was a change of purpose.
At first, they set out to build a
vaulted church with 20 m under the
vaults, in order for it to be lit
directly.
But at this stage of construction, in
the middle of the transept, they decided
to build 10 m higher. Plans were
changed. You can clearly see it in the
transept.
>> The first dome was [music] 20 m high,
the second 30 m, and the third was
supposed to have been 20 m high.
But the monks decided to go higher.
By placing this third dome 30 m high,
they were forced to shift the windows to
the north to leave room for the [music]
support pillar.
In their [music] dream of gigantism, raw
material was essential, and in that
respect, the location of the abbey was
perfect.
>> For materials, it was perfect.
Everything needed was on site, both in
abundance and quality.
That's exceptional.
There were limestone quarries.
If you limestone, you get lime, which is
the binder needed to build.
They had sand from the grown river and
large quantities of clay to make the
floors, tiles, etc.
Not to mention the valley was completely
covered with forests.
Near the construction site, [music] less
than 3 km away, were a multitude of
quarries with an abundance of stones.
The farthest one was 18 km away.
It's the last still visible today.
[music]
The monks extracted white limestone
called Pizolite limestone.
>> [music]
>> We're here at the light quarry. This is
one of the rare sources of soft stones
in the region.
We know that stone was extracted for
sculpture.
The other quarries were composed [music]
of hard stones used for construction.
There were three types of limestone with
different [music] physical
characteristics: micrite, oolite, and
crinoidal.
There was also arcos, [music]
a kind of sandstone.
The programs were deliberately very bold
in terms of budget and technique. So,
they looked for the best stone possible.
Large sheets of bedrock that could make
big walls.
The most beautiful stones were cut
directly on site and placed so that they
were visible on the exterior.
The walls were made with two facades
that were relatively similar with rubble
stone cut more or less finely depending
on the area.
>> [music]
>> And in the middle was a mixture of
coarse mortar with all types of stone
waste to create a stable uniform block.
The wider it was, the higher it could
go.
>> It was an [music] absolutely incredible
technical feat. They managed to build
something that was simply oversized for
the era with fairly simple means as the
walls were made with basic rubble.
That's how buildings have been
constructed since antiquity.
>> From these quarries, the monks extracted
a single stone [music] 6 m long, 3 m
high, and 45 cm thick.
The tympanum.
It was placed at the [music] entrance of
the large gate to impress visitors.
>> It was an extraordinary block in terms
of size considering the supply of the
local quarries.
Then it had to be moved which was also a
technical feat.
>> [music]
>> The idea was to use intelligence rather
than strength.
To carry the stone, [music] the monks
installed a ramp that compensated for
the slope of the valley over 10 m in
elevation.
The tympanum was then rolled on logs to
the large gate.
It was then [music] lifted up using a
hoisting device called a jack which
reduced the weight of the stone by a
factor of a hundred using the principle
of traction levers.
The 28-ton [music] stone was then placed
on its base.
>> This huge tympanum was lifted vertically
on these jambs and was then sculpted.
>> They didn't want to take the risk of
creating that sculpture of Christ in his
glory before setting it up and digging
into the mass of the tympanum.
Because of the 45 cm thickness, they dug
up to 40 cm to give depth to the
sculpture.
>> Christ was surrounded by four angels
[music] whose remains found on the site
show a quality of sculpture that was
unmatched at the time.
In certain areas of the tympanum, only 5
cm [music] of stone thickness remain.
>> From that moment on, an immense gate was
built that measured 14 m wide at the
base and 20 m high.
An architrave was placed at the top to
complete the composition.
This huge gate was hence designed as a
genuine triumphal arch.
This was really in line with the idea
that Cluny would be restoring the
ancient world and Rome.
>> The quality of the sculpture was just
breathtaking. When you came in through
the west door under that lintel, you
know, and then the whole sculpture of
the west door, [music] and you look down
the whole length of the church, what you
saw was the enormous Christ in the apse
painted.
>> [music]
>> There were more than 1,200 capitals
inside, which entails a gigantic number
of high-quality decorations.
These were large capitals, 80 cm wide by
80 cm high. It was a colossal building,
the scale of which was quite remarkable.
Only eight [music] capitals were found
almost intact.
They adorned the pillars of the
ambulatory in the chancel.
Here again, the sculpture was carved
with a lot of depth so as to play with
shadow and light.
>> The majority of the capitals had
Corinthian themes. They were modeled on
Corinthian capitals. The reference to
antiquity was tremendous.
>> In antiquity, you had samples with
columns and Corinthian capitals.
In the Cluny III, they replicated the
colonnade and borrowed Roman marble
columns that they trimmed and installed
around the chancel.
So, Cluny III was representative of
ancient Rome in all its splendor.
Above all, the monks wanted monumental
architecture.
With that 2-m diameter, the vestiges of
the pillars that punctuated the nave
bore witness to this desire.
The choice of the stones that [music]
composed them wasn't the result of
chance.
>> They didn't put just any stone in any
place. The base of the first pillars was
made of micrite limestone.
With moisture, the open transept and the
destruction, these stones degraded.
Next was a mixture of arcos and
limestone. Why did they use micrite
limestone, which is not particularly
known for being of good quality?
Well, that stone is interesting because
it's very resistant to compression.
What was above it was extremely heavy.
The pillars, the vaults, the dome all
weighed on the pillars.
So, they chose this stone to support the
vertical load.
>> Likewise, when the composition of the
walls of the still [music] existent
transept is analyzed, each stone has its
function.
At the base, micrite limestone [music]
to support the weight. In the middle,
strong and rigid sandstone. And at the
top, [music]
soft limestone for the sculpted
capitals.
At this point, 30 years had passed since
the first construction of the great
church, La Mayor Ecclesia. The Cluniac
order was at the height of its power.
>> The abbots were in permanent contact
with the emperor, sovereigns, leading
figures of the world, and the papacy.
The abbey couldn't be overlooked.
>> Gradually, they created what we called
an empire. They called it a religious
order, but it truly was an empire.
Today, for company or firm, it would be
called an empire.
It was an abbey that had subsidiaries,
so to speak, throughout Europe.
From England to Italy, from Spain to
Poland.
It had an enormous influence. Spiritual,
of course, but also temporal.
More than 800 monasteries were created
and directly attached to the abbey.
The order was based on the rule of St.
Benedict, a return [music] to spiritual
life and prayer.
It resonated with world leaders.
>> The abbots also put into place an entire
strategy around the worship of the dead.
The feast of the dead.
And the need to pray for the dead. They
multiplied the altars, held more and
more masses for the souls of the
deceased. And in each mass, obviously,
the coffers of the abbey increased.
>> Cluny had vast wealth at this time
and certain great sponsors.
And it's clearly was the kings of of
Leon and Castile.
Uh their their great gold [music]
treasury which they the tribute which
which came to Cluny annually
from the northwest [music] of Spain uh
meant that the coffers of Cluny were
bursting.
And uh
this incredibly ambitious [music]
uh church project was was undertaken.
>> Cluny had colossal means. It was a
building that was erected very quickly.
Perhaps too quickly because in 1125 an
event changed the structure of the
building.
>> In 1125 the vault of the nave allegedly
collapsed.
>> One of the vaults most likely collapsed.
We don't know where.
>> It could be
the great nave. It could be [music]
an aisle. Could just be a little aisle
or a chapel or something. You know, it's
not it's not at all clear. [music]
>> Obviously the monks were devastated.
Their dream of greatness and prestige
was ruined.
>> The monks had to [music] review their
plans and determine what happened. How
could a building that had been so well
thought out be fragile? What was the
mistake?
>> They didn't anticipate the fact that the
nave was very long.
The entire length of the nave had been
built using the same vault and the same
walls.
>> [music]
>> But given that length there was a
certain flexibility to it.
For example, if you take a pencil that's
5 cm long and you try to break it,
that's hard to do.
But with a 30 cm pencil all it takes is
a little snap and you break it. So what
did they do in the Middle Ages? They
constantly monitored the vaults. Cluny
would
The monks placed steep and narrow
staircases in the thick walls of the
Abbey, approximately 40 m in height.
From there, the monks could control the
structure. They might have noticed that
the vaults were fragile despite all of
their precautions.
>> What we do know is that they reinforced
the vault with walls called buttress
walls
in order to transfer some of the weight
and stabilize the vaults of the central
aisle.
And so avoid having massive walls that
would change the perspective a little,
an arch was hollowed out in them.
>> The arches thus counter balance the
forces applied by the vaults onto the
walls.
These arches would later emerge in
Gothic churches as flying buttresses.
>> Cluny III was really the transitional
building between typical classic
Romanesque art and Gothic art that would
flourish a few decades later.
It's traditionally believed that Gothic
art was developed in the Parisian region
and indeed most of the great monuments
of this period are concentrated there.
But the genius of the techniques that
allowed Gothic art to blossom really
took place in Cluny around 11:30.
>> In 1095, Pope Innocent II came to
consecrate the church. It wasn't
entirely finished. The last stone wasn't
laid until 11:30.
But as soon as it was completed, the
monks decided to build a 38-m long
narthex that would end with two large
towers called Barabans, culminating at
17 and 1/2 m.
There was a problem. The hill had to be
dug once again [music] to integrate the
extension.
They wanted the narthex to extend into
the hill.
The topography of the site and the
choice of location made by the monks at
the end of construction led to the fact
that one entered the church by going
down the steps.
Thus, bowing to the saint of saints
represented by the magnificent chancel
of Cluny III.
>> It was in Cluny that the legendary
narthex was created, an anti-church
located right in the front of the nave
called Galilee, because it refers to a
very specific liturgy pertaining to
Easter and the observance of Easter.
>> Easter celebrates the resurrection of
Jesus. In all its grandeur, the front of
the narthex [music] symbolized the
passage to eternal life.
The abbatial church was finally
finished. It had risen from the earth in
less than 70 years.
It imposed its power by its gigantism,
[music]
dominating the center of the abbey.
This religious city was surrounded by
walls.
Its ramparts [music] rose to more than 8
m and were made of defensive towers and
gates.
>> The walls of the Abbey weren't there
simply for the prestige. They were also
meant to protect in case of an attack,
and there were several.
And then you had the city around the
Abbey, along with the walls of the city.
So the Abbey was a small town within the
town of Cluny.
When the Abbey expanded, the
fortifications were enlarged as well,
and gradually by expanding
it brought more and more people to these
sites.
Pilgrims had to be accommodated, so a
hotel was built.
Visiting guests needed accommodating,
too.
We tend to forget that an Abbey isn't
just a church, a cloister, and a few
buildings.
It's an entire economic and cultural
complex.
>> Very quickly, the question of water
arose.
How could it be provided to the
community?
The monks resorted to two rivers located
on either side of the Abbey,
the Medasson and the Gronne.
But this required making adjustments.
>> The Medasson is a small stream that
originated west of Cluny
and was channeled under the city of
Cluny.
It was used for the hydraulics of the
monastery and part of the city.
The water from the source of the stream
was transported into the monastery as
drinking water.
It was brought to the fountain of the
cloister, and from there water was
distributed to the kitchen, to other
fountains, and perhaps to the baths.
>> The monks used gravity.
The slope went [music] from west to
east, and the Medasson flowed naturally
into the Gronne.
The fountain of the cloister that
received [music] the water was the
highest in the Abbey.
Once filled, it supplied the various
locations.
Using the drop in elevation, the monks
increased the pressure and made the
water gush.
The midasol [music] also served as sewer
water.
A parallel network was to be created
evacuating sewage.
>> There were sewer systems that were
several hundred meters long.
Running water was injected into them to
carry away the waste.
There were flushing systems upstream of
the monastic latrines,
which were large longitudinal buildings.
In these upstream systems,
the valves were opened and the fecal
matter was sent further downstream.
>> Very quickly, the Abbey expanded towards
the Grosne and the monks diverted the
course of the river. They set up water
retention ponds upstream and downstream
of the river by building 5 m high and
370 m long dams capable of holding 200
hectares of water.
In doing so, they created a diverted
canal that ran along the valley and
irrigated the entire Abbey.
It was one of the most complex hydronic
systems ever built in the Middle Ages.
>> Cluny took a natural water system and
changed it into a completely artificial
network.
There was no natural water passing
through the city or the Abbey at all.
>> The monks set up 187 mills along the
Grosne and inside the Abbey, which
brought them a colossal [music] income.
It was one of the greatest seigneurie of
the Middle Ages.
>> In the Middle Ages, mastering water was
of course a sign of power and
technological know-how.
The monks of Cluny were no exception.
Beyond the domestic dimension,
there's a spiritual dimension to water
that helped demonstrate the richness of
the Abbey.
>> [music]
>> The Cluny Abbey prospered [music] for
five centuries thanks to a succession of
powerful abbots.
The Abbey started to decline [music] in
the 15th century.
In the 16th century, it was no longer
attached to Rome and lost a large part
[music] of its income.
In 1789, the French Revolution brought
about the end of the Abbey with its sale
in 1798.
>> The bascial church was sold in lots to
material traders and developers.
Who stone after stone patiently
dismantled the entire building.
In this huge church, they was a
masterpiece of architecture, they only
saw a pile of stones that would allow
them to get richer.
>> The town encroached on a large part of
the Abbey.
Namely the land located close to the
village.
As a result, there is currently an
interweaving between the current town
and the historic buildings of the Abbey.
On the side completely deviated from the
concept of an Abbey.
Strolling through the city, one can see
a multitude of medieval houses, some of
which have pieces of the great Abbey in
their walls.
>> In the masonry of the houses and in
private owned gardens, we often see
elements of a sculpture, a piece of
capital, a fragment of a portal, or a
statuette that came from this great
church.
>> Over the centuries, the Abbey was
transformed. A new cloister was built on
the site of the old one in the 18th
[music] century.
As well as L'ecole des Arts et Metiers.
The gardens were redesigned.
But Cluny's great [music] abbatial
church lives on, scattered around the
city.
This architectural prowess in [music]
gigantism still radiates through its
vestiges.
>> It's true that relatively little
remains, but there is enough to get an
idea of what the Abbey was like if one
takes the time to look and really study.
>> Cluny as a site Cluny has to be earned.
It isn't just handed to you on a silver
platter. You have to dig.
And when you're given the opportunity to
do so,
you'll find it's wonderful.
>> Every detail [music] immerses you in the
glorious past of this prestigious order.
It's thanks to the power and fervor of
[music] the abbots that the Abbey was
able to compete with the greatest
buildings to the point of being compared
to Rome.
By wanting to [music] create bigger and
higher, these monk builders advanced the
architecture of the Middle Ages.
Today, all you have to do [music] is let
yourself be carried by these premises to
understand the scale of this project and
its challenges.
>> [music]
>> Oh.